"Side Effects of Water Fluoridation: Dental Fluorosis"
Fluoride research
over a half century
has historically established
water fluoridation to be safe
when used at typical
fluoridation doses
of one part per million.
However, naturally
fluoridated waters
up around two parts per million
can put children
under the age of nine
at increased risk
for dental fluorosis,
and a lifetime of drinking water
at four ppm can cause
skeletal fluorosis and increase
the risk of bone fractures.
You can see these kinds of
levels in the Earth's natural
fluoride belts that extend
from Turkey through Iraq, Iran,
and Afghanistan
to China and Japan.
The reason susceptibility
to dental fluorosis ends
at around eight years old
is that's when enamel
maturation is completed,
before our final permanent teeth
finish erupting.
After teeth are formed,
dental fluorosis can no longer
develop or worsen.
At one ppm, one part
per million of fluoride,
public health authorities
estimated that less than
10 percent of kids
would develop the condition,
and only in its mildest forms.
We've since learned that
the prevalence and severity
of fluorosis is much higher
than predicted.
According to the CDC,
about a third of American
children now have some form
of dental fluorosis,
with about one in 30
experiencing
a moderate to severe case.
This may reflect exposure
to multiple fluoride sources
not factored into
the original calculations.
Now, most fluorosis is so mild
as to be hardly noticeable,
taking the form
of white streaks or splotches
visible only to dentists
under the bright lights
of their exam chair.
But serious cases can involve
severe pitting and discoloration
and present more than just
a cosmetic defect.
For example, one study found
that children with severe cases
are more likely to be viewed by
their peers as less attractive,
less careful, less clean,
less happy, less healthy,
less intelligent, less kind,
less reliable, less social.
Imagine what that could do
to a kid's self-esteem.
Given the higher-than-expected
rates of fluorosis,
in 2015,
the U.S. Public Health Service
reduced the recommended fluoride
concentration of drinking water
down to 0.7 ppm
across the board.
Previously, levels were set at
up to 1.2 ppm in cooler areas
where people tend
to drink less water.
This change would be estimated
to keep the percentage
of those developing fluorosis
of "aesthetic concern"
down to approximately
12 percent.
In terms of other health
concerns, until recently,
mainstream medicine's view might
have perhaps best been summed up
by the final statement in
an exhaustive report published
by Consumer Reports in 1978:
"The simple truth is that
there is no
scientific controversy
over the safety of fluoridation.
The practice is safe,
economical, and beneficial.
The survival
of this fake controversy,
in the Consumer Union's opinion,
is one of the major triumphs
of quackery over science
in our generation."
In the last few years, though,
there have been growing concerns
about the adverse effects
of fluoride
on brain development,
which I'll address next.